<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>My (in)frequent musings on Somnath Rakshit</title><link>https://somnathr.com/musings/</link><description>Recent content in My (in)frequent musings on Somnath Rakshit</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://somnathr.com/musings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Git Command Collection</title><link>https://somnathr.com/musings/git_commands/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://somnathr.com/musings/git_commands/</guid><description>My Git Command Collection Table Of Contents Before You Begin Saving Uncommitted Changes How to undo all uncommitted changes How to undo some uncommitted changes Do you have uncommitted stuff in your working directory? Discarding all local commits on this branch Replacing all branch history/contents Removing the last commit Reworking the last commit Moving a commit from one branch to another Undoing the last few git operations affecting HEAD/my branch&amp;rsquo;s tip Like many other people, I tend to be frustrated often trying to find the right command while using Git.</description></item><item><title>A Comprehensive Guide to Sorting in Pandas</title><link>https://somnathr.com/musings/sorting_in_pandas/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://somnathr.com/musings/sorting_in_pandas/</guid><description>A Comprehensive Guide to Sorting in Pandas In order to sort rows in Pandas, you can use the sort_values() function. I have taken examples from this excellant blog. Although it shows a lot of the use cases covered here, the last case is absent pretty much everywhere.
In this tutorial, I will be showing how to use Pandas to sort rows based on different criterion.
You can run a colab notebook containing all code present in this post by clicking here.</description></item></channel></rss>