<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Somnath Rakshit</title>
    <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Somnath Rakshit, 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 02:32:45 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural Style Transfer</title>
      <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/neural-style-transfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 02:32:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/neural-style-transfer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Google Photos album containing the images is present &lt;a href=&#34;https://photos.app.goo.gl/GmeSraqqvKPxu7Zb6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implemented the neural style transfer algortihm implemented by Gatys et al. (2016) in PyTorch. This technique allows us to take an input image and perform its reproduction in a new artistic style. This algorithm takes two images as inputs. One is the style image that contains the artistic style whereas the other image contains the content which is to be modified in the given artistic style.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>geograpy3</title>
      <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/geograpy3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 02:42:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/geograpy3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;geograpy3 is a fork of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Corollarium/geograpy2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Geograpy2&lt;/a&gt;, which is itself a fork of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ushahidi/geograpy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;geograpy&lt;/a&gt; and inherits most of it, but solves several problems (such as support for utf8, places names with multiple words, confusion over homonyms etc). Also, geograpy3 is compatible with Python 3, unlike Geography2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is installable from PyPi by running the following command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install geograpy3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detection and Localisation of Diabetic Retinopathy</title>
      <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/fundus-image-localization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 01:21:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/fundus-image-localization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vQpi7z7g1swVv-bcG2GeYggnhCjL1zXOq3BJYMXnqGtJC6pVg7Iq7qr-4bODfVGEcngX9PGiuJ5P8Qs/pub?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=15000&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://somnathrakshit.github.io/files/download/project_report_jgec.pdf&#34;&gt;Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diabetic retinopathy occurs when the retina is damaged because fluids leak from blood vessels into the retina. The presence of hemorrhage is one of the earliest signs to indicate the severity of the disease. In this paper we review techniques, algorithms and methodologies used for the detection of hemorrhage from diabetic retinopathy retinal images. The retina is a transparent layer of vascularized neural tissue lining the inner layer of the back wall of the eye, between the retinal pigment epithelium on the outer and the vitreous on the inner side. The retina captures photons and converts these two photochemical and electrical energy integrates the Signals and transmits the resultant signal to the visual cortex of the brain via the optic nerve tracts and radiations. The retinal architecture is lamellar. Within this there are major types performing sensory nutritional regulatory immunomodulatory and structure and functions. The retina is uniquely partitioned from the vascular system by the blood retinal barrier and blood aqueous barrier. The blood supply is dual to the inner retina it is by the retinal circulation lying within the in a retina and to the outer retina it is by the choroidal circulation, Hrithik vascular layer lying outside of the retinal pigment epithelium. The retinal pigment epithelium and the choroid are critical to retinal function. Is the eye is imagined to be a camera in the retina is the film. Just like a picture cannot be developed if the camera has defective film, vision is not possible in an eye with a defective retina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If caught early then diabetic retinopathy can be treated, otherwise it can lead to irreversible blindness. Unluckily, medical specialists capable of detecting the disease are not available in many parts of the world where diabetes is prevalent. Deep neural networks have helped in solving many such problems in the recent past. Medical image classification has been done accurately using deep neural networks and thus, we will be using this in our project. The aim of this project is to use deep learning to help doctors identify the patients in need, particularly among underserved populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prolonged diabetes leads to DR, where the retina is damaged due to fluid leaking from the blood vessels. Usually, the stage of DR is judged based on blood vessels, exudes, hemorrhages, microaneurysms and texture. In this paper, we have discussed different methods for features extraction and automatic DR stage detection. An ophthalmologist uses an ophthalmoscope to visualize the blood vessels and his or her brain to detect the DR stages. Recently digital imaging became available as a tool for DR screening. It provides high quality permanent records of the retinal appearance, which can be used for monitoring of progression or response to treatment, and which can be reviewed by an ophthalmologist, digital images have the potential to be processed by automatic analysis systems. A combination of both accurate and early diagnosis as well as correct application of treatment can prevent blindness caused by DR in more than 50% of all cases. Therefore, regular screenings for DR of patients with diabetes is important. The grading of the resultant fundus images is an important cost factor. Automated DR detection can reduce the grading cost and thereby make the whole screening process less expensive. Some of the algorithms and systems reviewed in this paper are close to achieve DR identification in clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Piezoelectric Transducer and Arduino Based Wirelessly Controlled Energy Saving Scheme for Street Lights</title>
      <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/energy-saving-scheme-street-lights/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 03:19:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/energy-saving-scheme-street-lights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, a large amount of energy is wasted on continuously lighting street lights. In this paper, a scheme has been proposed to automatically control street lights using Arduino microcontroller and switch on lights only when an activity is observed in the road. Also, a scheme has been discussed to generate power and run our automated model using Piezoelectric transducers. Additionally, it is shown how this system can be used for other purposes like traffic monitoring, weather monitoring and fault checking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the proposed system, the developing countries can be more efficient with their electrical energy as well as the maintenance cost of power lines for street lights. It also reduces the manual work to zero. Automatic Smart Light System is a very user friendly approach and the usage of this smart light system will help in saving large amount of power in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Land Patterns from Satellite Imagery in Amazon Rainforest using Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/identify-land-pattern-keras/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 23:52:39 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/identify-land-pattern-keras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Amazon rainforests have been suffering widespread damage, both via natural and artificial means. Every minute, it is estimated that the world loses forest cover the size of 48 football fields. Deforestation in the Amazon rainforest has led to drastically reduced biodiversity, loss of habitat, climate change and other biological losses. In this respect, it has become essential to track how the nature of these forests change over time. Image classification using deep learning can help speed up this process by removing the manual task of classifying each image. Here, it is shown how convolutional neural networks can be used to track changes in land patterns in the Amazon rainforests. In this work, a testing accuracy of 96.71% was obtained. This can help governments and other agencies to track changes in land patterns more effectively and accurately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/somnathrakshit/334297f8ab77aa6739d97284d16addd9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Code,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://somnathrakshit.github.io/files/download/ICNDE.pdf&#34;&gt;Poster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//gist.github.com/somnathrakshit/334297f8ab77aa6739d97284d16addd9.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
