<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Somnath Rakshit</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/</link><atom:link href="https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Somnath Rakshit, 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 03:13:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/img/avatar.jpg</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/</link></image><item><title>Answerability Classification Using Hand-Crafted Features</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/vizwiz/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 03:13:05 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/vizwiz/</guid><description>&lt;p>Competing with the members in your class on a challenge to predict whether a visual question is answerable. For this task, we were required to create a multi-modal (computer vision + natural language processing) classification system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Microsoft Azure Vision API has been used to obtain the tags for each image. They have been joined together with space character in between to create artifical sentence. Then, the TF-IDF representation for these artificially generated sentences are created to be used as features. The TF-IDF representation for the questions have been created as features.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The two TF-IDF matrices are now stacked horizontally to create the unified feature set. We use this as the input dataset for our machine learning model. Random forest model has been used for this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, we see that the dataset is imbalanced. Thus, we try to resample the dataset so that the minority class has equal number of samples as the majority class. We do this by randomly copying the samples. Finally, with this resampled dataset, we once again run a random forest classifier. We see that the results improve.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, we run Grid Search to find the best hyperparameter for the random forest model and test it on the validation set, which has not been resampled. We see that when the number of estimators is equal to 1000, random forest model performs the best with accuracy metric.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Neural Style Transfer</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/neural-style-transfer/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 02:32:45 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/neural-style-transfer/</guid><description>&lt;p>Google Photos album containing the images is present
&lt;a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/GmeSraqqvKPxu7Zb6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Implemented the neural style transfer algortihm implemented by Gatys et al. (2016) in PyTorch. This technique allows us to take an input image and perform its reproduction in a new artistic style. This algorithm takes two images as inputs. One is the style image that contains the artistic style whereas the other image contains the content which is to be modified in the given artistic style.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>geograpy3</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/geograpy3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 02:42:18 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/geograpy3/</guid><description>&lt;p>geograpy3 is a fork of
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Corollarium/geograpy2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geograpy2&lt;/a>, which is itself a fork of
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ushahidi/geograpy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">geograpy&lt;/a> and inherits most of it, but solves several problems (such as support for utf8, places names with multiple words, confusion over homonyms etc). Also, geograpy3 is compatible with Python 3, unlike Geography2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is installable from PyPi by running the following command.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>pip install geograpy3&lt;/code>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Piezoelectric Transducer and Arduino Based Wirelessly Controlled Energy Saving Scheme for Street Lights</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/energy-saving-scheme-street-lights/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 03:19:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/energy-saving-scheme-street-lights/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, a large amount of energy is wasted on continuously lighting street lights. In this paper, a scheme has been proposed to automatically control street lights using Arduino microcontroller and switch on lights only when an activity is observed in the road. Also, a scheme has been discussed to generate power and run our automated model using Piezoelectric transducers. Additionally, it is shown how this system can be used for other purposes like traffic monitoring, weather monitoring and fault checking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the proposed system, the developing countries can be more efficient with their electrical energy as well as the maintenance cost of power lines for street lights. It also reduces the manual work to zero. Automatic Smart Light System is a very user friendly approach and the usage of this smart light system will help in saving large amount of power in the world.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Identifying Land Patterns from Satellite Imagery in Amazon Rainforest using Deep Learning</title><link>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/identify-land-pattern-keras/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 23:52:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://somnathrakshit.github.io/project/identify-land-pattern-keras/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Amazon rainforests have been suffering widespread damage, both via natural and artificial means. Every minute, it is estimated that the world loses forest cover the size of 48 football fields. Deforestation in the Amazon rainforest has led to drastically reduced biodiversity, loss of habitat, climate change and other biological losses. In this respect, it has become essential to track how the nature of these forests change over time. Image classification using deep learning can help speed up this process by removing the manual task of classifying each image. Here, it is shown how convolutional neural networks can be used to track changes in land patterns in the Amazon rainforests. In this work, a testing accuracy of 96.71% was obtained. This can help governments and other agencies to track changes in land patterns more effectively and accurately.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/somnathrakshit/334297f8ab77aa6739d97284d16addd9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Code,&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://somnathrakshit.github.io/files/download/ICNDE.pdf">Poster&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;script type="application/javascript" src="https://gist.github.com/somnathrakshit/334297f8ab77aa6739d97284d16addd9.js">&lt;/script></description></item></channel></rss>